<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Matt Marsico&#x27;s Portfolio</title>
    <subtitle>A compilation of all of my interests and snapshot into my life</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://mattmarsico.com/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mattmarsico.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mattmarsico.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Sports Betting Strategy</title>
        <published>2025-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mattmarsico.com/blog/sports-betting/"/>
        <id>https://mattmarsico.com/blog/sports-betting/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mattmarsico.com/blog/sports-betting/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sports-betting-strategy&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sports-betting-strategy&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sports-betting-strategy&quot;&gt;Sports Betting Strategy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sports betting goes back thousands of years and has long been a pastime for sports enthusiasts.
Unfortunately, it can turn into an addiction, or be the precursor to financial ruin for many individuals.
Recently, I have developed an interest in statistics-based sports betting. I compare it
to something like counting cards in a casino. Not illegal, but you will be limited very quickly when Vegas finds out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sports-betting-vs-stock-market&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sports-betting-vs-stock-market&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sports-betting-vs-stock-market&quot;&gt;Sports Betting vs. Stock Market&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sports-betting has shocking similarity to the stock market
in more ways than one. Both have strategies for winning, yet nobody knows the real result until it happens.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my focus as a developer is in the algorithmic side of either trading or betting, I noticed that many of
the strategies for either market remain largely the same, with a common emphasis on statistics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I highlight this comparison is to explain that I am not just throwing money away, and that responsible or informed gambling can be equally profitable.
I could also use this to poke fun at stockbrokers but I&#x27;ll leave that to you. (Gamblers in suits)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;statistics-in-sports-betting&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#statistics-in-sports-betting&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: statistics-in-sports-betting&quot;&gt;Statistics in Sports Betting&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have mentioned that there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; strategies for applying stats in sports betting, I should probably explain what they are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental concept for any type of wager is &lt;strong&gt;expected value&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you have taken a stats class already I will remind you that it is
a weighted average of all possible values of a random variable. If you have not taken a stats class, consider the following:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are offered a bet on a fair coin flip. If it is heads, you win \$10. If it is tails, you lose \$5.
You know that the probability of it being heads is 50% and tails is also 50%. You then multiply the
probability of each outcome by the value obtained from that corresponding outcome. In this case:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 0.5 \times $10 + 0.5 \times -$5 = $2.50 $$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that every time you play, you are expected to win \$2.50. If you played 100 times, you&#x27;d expect about a \$250 profit in the long run.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expected value is the backbone of smart sports betting. I will reference it many times in subsequent sections.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-the-true-odds&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-are-the-true-odds&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-are-the-true-odds&quot;&gt;What are the True Odds?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your next question may be, &quot;how can you get the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; probabilities of some type of sports bet?&quot;. The short answer is there is no answer. There will
never be an exactly correct probability of a certain outcome. In practice, there are a variety of methods to developing a &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; line. I will outline a few.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;consensus-line&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#consensus-line&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: consensus-line&quot;&gt;Consensus Line&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One approach you could take is to average all odds for a specific bet into an &quot;average&quot; line. This may give you a solid baseline for what most sportsbooks
are asking for, but it is important to acknowledge two critical pieces of information. The first is that there are fewer oddsmakers than you realize. Often times
sportsbooks will just react to an industry-standard oddsmaker, instead of determining a fair line themselves. The second is that some sportsbooks are better
at setting fair odds than others.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharp-vs-non-sharp-soft-sportsbooks&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sharp-vs-non-sharp-soft-sportsbooks&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sharp-vs-non-sharp-soft-sportsbooks&quot;&gt;Sharp vs Non-Sharp &#x2F; Soft Sportsbooks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can often tell how good a sporstbook is at setting odds by how much they limit their users. A sportsbook like Pinnacle is referred to as &quot;sharp&quot;, because
their lines are extremely competitive and they don&#x27;t limit winning players. Think of a casino that does not kick you out for counting cards. They make their money
through tiny margins in the odds called &quot;vig&quot;, so they have an advantage in the long run.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, many sportsbooks cater to your average joe (not a professional gambler). In these cases, they will limit you if you start to win too much money.
This is often because they are slower to adjust their lines or they focus more on entertainment than line accuracy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharp-sportsbook-consensus&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sharp-sportsbook-consensus&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sharp-sportsbook-consensus&quot;&gt;Sharp Sportsbook Consensus&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings me to another solution to finding the fair line - the sharp sportsbook consensus. Instead of averaging the lines of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; sportsbooks, you just average
the most statistically-accurate books. This gives you a better representation of the true odds, because many sharp sportsbooks change their lines in response
to small details about the game like whether the pitcher tweets about wrist pain before the game. This will likely be the best way to determine a fair line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know where to get the data to determine a fair line, let&#x27;s talk about how to actually calculate it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;odds-conversion-and-removing-vig&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#odds-conversion-and-removing-vig&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: odds-conversion-and-removing-vig&quot;&gt;Odds Conversion and Removing Vig&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember vig? We need to get rid of that small margin to determine the true odds of the outcome. The odds that they give you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be converted into percentages,
but they will be skewed by vig, so we must remember to remove it. Consider the following example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using American Odds: Team A has a line of -130 and Team B has a line of +120.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is to convert the American Odds to their implied probabilities:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team A (negative): $$ p = \frac{a}{a + 100} = \frac{130}{130 + 100} = 0.565217 $$
Team B (positive): $$ p = \frac{100}{b + 100} = \frac{100}{120 + 100} = 0.454545 $$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we sum these odds we notice that $ 0.565217 + 0.454545 = 1.019763 $. That extra few decimals over 1.0 is the vig.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is to remove this from our calculation. We accomplish this by &lt;em&gt;normalizing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it to 100%.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ p_{fair^A} = 0.565217 &#x2F; 1.019763 = 0.554264 = 55.4264\% $$
$$ p_{fair^B} = 0.454545 &#x2F; 1.019763 = 0.445736 = 44.5736\% $$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congrats! You now have a probability of each outcome without the margin. You can now leverage this information in your future bets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;placing-the-bets-and-limitations&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#placing-the-bets-and-limitations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: placing-the-bets-and-limitations&quot;&gt;Placing the Bets and Limitations&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have an accurate probability of the outcomes, you can calculate the expected value and determine if you will face long-run success.
However, there are a few roadblocks you will face.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lines are recomputed often and can affect your calculations. Take care in confirming your calculations are still relevent when you place a slip.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you win too much, many sportsbooks will limit you. Beware of this and factor it into your strategy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some sportsbooks are softer in specific sports or markets. Do some research to find which ones may expose an edge for you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; lose, have trust in the long-run effects. Many parlay strategies have around a 20% win rate. Winning 20% of the time does not sound
great but you &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; hold out, and you will have success over time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck and enjoy!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>About Me</title>
        <published>2025-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mattmarsico.com/aboutme/"/>
        <id>https://mattmarsico.com/aboutme/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://mattmarsico.com/aboutme/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#who-am-i&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who Am I?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Matt Marsico. I am a musician, programmer, and hobbyist. My interests span across technology, music, fitness, and more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#music&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-beginning&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-beginning&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-beginning&quot;&gt;The Beginning&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first passion was music. I started playing guitar in 2014 and I was enthralled since the day I first picked it up. I remember
the day I decided to learn was when I first played &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Rocksmith_2014&quot;&gt;Rocksmith 2014&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
at my uncle&#x27;s house in May of 2014. American Idiot by Green Day was the first song I played on guitar.
Not a week after that I ordered my first guitar which was a short scale length
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fender.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;mini-stratocaster&quot;&gt;Squire Mini Stratocaster&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which was delivered on June 6, 2014.
I was self-taught for the first two years of my guitar-playing journey. I learned through Rocksmith which was
a surprisingly good resource for getting started. I say surprisingly loosly because it is literally designed to
be used as a learning tool but it is also a video game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;school-of-rock&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#school-of-rock&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: school-of-rock&quot;&gt;School of Rock&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started taking lessons at School of Rock in 2016, and my first show was Cheap Trick and Aerosmith. The program handled
the booking of shows, song selection, and gear. It was a great way to get into performing and allowed me to connect
with other music-minded individuals. I then went on to perform in a variety of other shows like Glam Rock, Led Zeppelin,
Riot Fest, The Who, The Beatles, British Invasion, Pink Floyd, and Rush. I also joined the House Band which was a more
experienced group of musicians that played shows a few times a month.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setlists were so varied I can hardly remember half of the songs we played, but it was an incredible introduction
to music of the past and present and allowed me to discover other bands through my friends there. With professional
teachers I learned quickly and even played at places like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.summerfest.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Summerfest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in Milwaukee.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;images&#x2F;IMG_6550.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Young Matt Performing&quot; class=&quot;article-image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-school&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#high-school&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: high-school&quot;&gt;High School&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High School was a change as it always is and I was extremely excited to look into our school&#x27;s Rock Band. It is
a rare opportunity that very few schools offer and fewer promote as much as ours. Our Rock Band was the premiere band
at the school and also had the benefit of getting some solid funding for performances. We played at masses, plays,
sporting events like basketball and volleyball games, and even had our own performances. It was very well integrated
in the school and it showed. During my freshman year I applied to be in the Rock Band which was an uncommon thing to do
as the band is often reserved for upperclassmen. However, I stubbornly applied and was able to impress the band director
enough to get a spot as the first freshman to make it into the band. I made an immediate impact and my previous experience
showed, as I was able to secure lead parts for most of the songs. It was a great way to meet some upperclassmen that I would
otherwise rarely interact with and bring my passion with me to my school. My freshman year of high school was also the year
I decided to pick up programming - a hobby that would eventually overshadow but far from extinguish my interest in playing guitar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued to play in the Rock Band throughout high school where I picked up some serious experience that led to me taking on
a leadership role in the band. I started creating setlists and organizing rehearsals, but tried my best to maintain the scope
of my role and stay humble - a difficult task for a high school guitarist. Both my Freshman and Junior years of high school&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
we even played at Disney World and Universal Studios. I still need to find the video of me playing a guitar solo at night
on the Disney Springs Waterside Stage with the Hard Rock Cafe Volcano erupting in the background.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;programming&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#programming&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: programming&quot;&gt;Programming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-beginning-again&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-beginning-again&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-beginning-again&quot;&gt;The Beginning (Again)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My programming journey started through two pivotal experiences. First, I was enrolled in a mandatory technology literacy class
in my High School that assigned a project of programming a game in Scratch as a sort of final project. Being the zealous
teen that I was, I decided that I was going to be cooler than everyone else and write the game in Python instead of Scratch.
I used the Pygame framework to create the first example app that made it hard to understand how the framework worked. It
was the most disgusting code I have ever written, but it worked, and that game had me hooked. It was difficult
but was the canon event that all programmers experience defined by frustration and an intense sense of accomplishment at it&#x27;s
completion. As you can tell by now I tend to get obsessed with my interests and programming was no different. I started
learning on my own and building crappy apps, playing with [Raspberry Pis] and tinkering in general, bringing me to my next
pivotal experience. Covid-19 shut down my school in the late months of 2019 allowing me plenty of time to do whatever the
hell I wanted. Although Covid was a tragic time for many people with families experiencing loss of grandparents, parents,
and time spent together, it was an incredible opportunity for me to hone my craft. I would play guitar for hours and then
do some programming. This is when I decided to build my own PC. Everyone and their mom decided to build a desktop around
that time due to all the remote work, but I somehow got in early enough to maintain some of the funds in my piggy bank.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around my Sophomore year of high school I switched to Linux where I started with Ubuntu. I distro-hopped for a while experimenting
with Arch, Manjaro, and OpenSuse. I eventually settled on Manjaro for a while because I was not savvy enough to manage my
operating system but arrogant (insecure?) enough to need something to brag about. Yes I know it isn&#x27;t the same as Arch. This
continued as I messed around with Raspberry Pis and learned the command line. I believe that my switch to Linux solidified my
interest in programming and provided me with an environment that made programming enjoyable and fun.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started taking programming classes in my High School where I exceled due to my existing experience and even worked for our
school&#x27;s IT help desk where I assisted other students in diagnosing issues with their laptops. This also earned me some
fancy-schmancy administrator priviledges that let me install programming software and music-related tools like Axe-Edit
on my school laptop. There were definitely some days where I paid far more attention to a program I was writing than whatever
class I was in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-interests&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#other-interests&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: other-interests&quot;&gt;Other Interests&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever Wintertime rolls around I have my annual desire to become an X-Games level snowboarder. I started my winter sports
journey as a skiier where became the fastest moving object&#x2F;toddler on the mountain (Pizza is for losers). Eventually, I
decided to give snowboarding a try. I have never looked back and still love taking a few days during the winter to hit the
local hills or even take a trip out west.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been playing soccer since I was almost 4 years old. I played park district soccer, then club, and for my high school
team as well. Although it was never my primary interest, it became a hell of a lot more fun when I started lifting weights,
another hobby of mine. Not to say I am that muscular, but soccer players tend to have a very lean build that does not lend well
to a 180 lb aggressive high-schooler. When I was younger I was not the biggest fan of soccer but I am glad I stayed involved
as it kept me in shape and gives me a fun activity at University with Intramural Soccer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
